Speaker1:
(Transcribed by Sonix.ai - Remove this message by upgrading your Sonix account)
I distinguish two types of work.
One is the weekend seminar,
which is a kind of sampling where you get
acquainted with our approach and those of you
who want to work are welcome,
and you see that you will learn a lot by
participating.
You're also free to interrupt and make
comments.
Usually I do not answer questions because I
don't believe there are answers.
I believe we are always looking for the right
question to the answer,
which is already given beforehand.
Which immediately leads us to what I believe
are the two key words in Gestalt therapy.
These two key words, if you understand them.
I believe you have the whole story.
The two key words are now and how.
2 or 3 letter words. This sounds very
simple. At the same time.
I have to warn you, because to get to that
spontaneity and authenticity which we in our
endeavor of bringing about possibly a
humanistic revolution.
You already have a certain amount of
humanistic rebellion,
but not yet a revolution.
But to bring about that state.
To save the genuineness of the human being.
Or let me talk and try religious terms to
regain our soul,
or to talk in American terms,
to revive the American corpse and make him
bring him back to life.
Now, the paradox is to get this spontaneity
we need,
just like in Zen, an utmost discipline.
And the discipline is simply to understand,
to break it off.
Anything that is not contained in the words
now and how.
I know you used to ask why?
Like every child, like every immature person.
Ask why? To get rationalizations or
explanations.
But the why at best leads to a clever,
clever explanation,
but not never to an understanding.
So let me say a few words more about the two
words now and how.
The dogma is nothing exists except the now.
And now is the present,
is the phenomenon is what you are aware of.
It is that moment. In which you carry your
so-called memories.
And your so-called anticipations with you.
The past is not more. The past is past.
And the past. What happened in the past is
either assimilated.
And has become a part of us.
Or we carry around an unfinished situation.
An incomplete gestalt.
Let me give you an example.
The most famous of the unfinished situations
is the fact that we have not forgiven our
parents. Especially if we are beset with the
curse
of perfectionism. Or idealism.
Then we discover our parents are never right.
Or marriages. The husband or the wife is
never right because they don't measure up to
this impossible yardstick of the ideal.
The perfectionist in marriage,
for instance,
is not in love with his wife,
his love with his ideal.
And he demands from his wife that she should
fit into this Procrustes bed of this ideal,
and she blames her if she does not fit.
What this ideal exactly is,
he would not reveal.
Now and then there might be some
characteristics,
but the essence of the ideal is that it is
impossible.
Unobtainable. Just a good opportunity to
swing the whip.
If you carry this ideal,
this perfectionistic ideal around with
yourself, you have a wonderful tool to play
the beloved game of the neurotic,
the self-torture game.
There is no end to the self-torture and to
the self nagging self castigating.
It hides under the mask of self improvement.
It never works. It will come across all the
constellation,
the how it can not work.
Now switching back to the now.
Now I am pulling out of my drawer the
memories.
And possibly believe that these memories are
identical with my history.
It's never true. We abstract certain
experiences
from the world and then file it away as
memory.
And if the memory, then.
Is unpleasant. Especially if it's unpleasant
to our self-esteem,
we change it. None of the so-called Freudian
traumata has ever been proved
to exist. These traumata are always
falsification,
or in most cases, inventions.
I suggest that you read a beautiful little
pocket book called I Never Promised You a
Rose garden. We've got such an instance about
this invented memory.
And the whole illness is supposed to be based
on this memory.
No wonder that all the wild goose chase of
the psychoanalyst to find out why I am now
like this can never come to an end.
Can never prove A real opening up of the
person himself.
Now the same applies to the future.
It seems incredible that we should live
without goals.
Without worrying about the future.
That we could be open and ready for what
might come.
No, we have to take insurance policies.
We have to make sure that we have no future,
that the status quo should remain,
or maybe even be a bit better.
But we mustn't take risks.
We mustn't be open that something should
happen that would be new and exciting.
And contributing to our growth.
So much for the now. For the time being.
Now the how. Is all we need to understand.
The way we or the world functions.
The how gives us perspective orientation.
The how shows that the basic one of the basic
laws,
the identity of structure and function is
valid.
We change the structure.
The function changes. We change the function,
the structure changes.
The hardest perspective.
The Y gives only an unending inquiry in a
cause of a cause,
of a cause, of a cause,
of a cause, of a cause.
And as Freud has already observed,
every event is overdetermined.
It has many causes from all kinds of things.
Sides come together in order to create the
specific moment that is the now.
Many factors come together to create this
specific,
unique person, which is I.
Nobody can at any given moment be different
from what he is at this moment,
including all the wishes and prayers that he
should be different.
We are what we are. Now
the next objection is how do we bring about
changes?
Apparently there are lots of changes that are
desirable.
To take one instance,
this unpleasant habit of self-torture.
The answer is changes occur by themselves.
Once the different items are recognized and
fall into their place.
The road to hell is paved with good
intentions.
Any attention to exchange will achieve the
opposite.
You know, all this New Year's resolution.
The desperation of being different.
The attempt to control yourself.
How this always comes to naught or in extreme
cases when you really apparently successful
up to the point where the nervous breakdown
occurs.
The final way out. Here again,
once we
recognize the structure of our behavior.
Which in the case of self-improvement,
is the split between a top dog and an
underdog. And we understand how by listening,
we bring about a reconciliation of the two
fighting clowns.
Or tragic people. Then we realized that we
cannot deliberately bring
about changes in ourselves and in others.
The Topdog underdog split works about like
this.
The character differs somewhat,
but there are certain structures in common.
The Topdog usually is righteous,
knows best.
The top dog is a bully and works with you
should and you should not.
The top dog threatens.
If you don't, then there will be catastrophes
such as you won't be loved,
you won't get to heaven,
you will die, and so on and so on.
All the threads of the top dog,
the underdog has no power.
The underdog is the Mickey Mouse.
The top dog is the super mouse.
And the underdog works like this.
Yeah. Manana I try my best.
Look, I try again and again.
I can't help it if I fail I can't help it if
I forgot your birthday.
I had such good intentions.
You see the underdog. The underdog is coming.
An underdog strive for control.
Like every parent and every child,
they have each other for control.
Now again, the ways of manipulation of the
top dog are very simple.
Usually, the top dog manipulates with threats
and demands.
The underdog manipulates with being
defensive,
apologetic, wheedling,
playing the crybaby and such things,
and will come across a lot about if we come
to talk about the means and ways,
how we manipulate each other,
how we manipulate ourselves in ourselves,
and the eternal struggle.
It is only one purpose to keep the status quo
of the neurosis intact.
Maybe we have an opportunity here to see that
one can get through the status quo.
If you can't get through the impasse that
keeps the bad,
marriage bad and exhausting instead of
satisfactory,
that keeps the relationship of the therapist
with the patient in the status quo going on
for years and years. Again,
the condition is
and this is the key right now,
I can only hypnotize you,
persuade you, make you believe that I'm
right.
You don't know. I'm just preaching something.
You won't learn from my words.
Learning is discovery.
There's no other means of effective learning.
You can tell a child a thousand times.
The stove is hot. Doesn't help.
The child has to discover it for himself.
And I hope I can assist you in learning,
in discovering something about yourself.
Maybe I can also assist you in learning
something more about the two worlds than now
in the how. I'd like to say a few words about
the two levels on which we live.
The usual idea we encounter is that we see
the human being as one with a dichotomy
between mind and body.
Body and soul, or whatever dichotomy you
choose if this were true?
We always all would be corpses inhabited in
Habited by a ghost.
And this goes on after death can fly away
into heaven.
And the corpse is being burned.
But in the meantime, it must be alive.
It's difficult to assume that such could be
the split.
You see every organism starting as a unit,
a germ in a plane.
And this unit difference here.
Could you differentiate in opposites?
Right, left, up, down and so on.
So we are still left with a question.
What then is this thing we call mind?
The answer was first given by Freud.
You see, Freud had devoted his whole life.
To prove to himself and to others that sex is
not bad.
And he had to prove that,
as in his time, the scientific approach was
that of causality. That the trouble was
caused by something in the past like a
billiard cue. Pushing a billiard ball in the
cue is then the cause of the rolling of the
ball in the meantime. Our scientific attitude
has changed.
We don't look to the world anymore in terms
of cause and effect.
We look upon the world as a continuous,
ongoing process.
We are back to her cry to the pre-Socratic
Panteri.
Everything is in flux.
We never step into the same river twice.
In other words, we have made in science,
but unfortunately not yet in psychiatry.
The transition from one linear causality to
thinking process from the why to the how.
Now for it. When he saw the one thing what he
called thinking is
probably thinking is rehearsing.
You see, if he had accepted the statement of
his thinking is rehearsing,
he would have realized that our activity is
turned towards the future.
Because we rehearse for the future.
Now. This is not the situation.
We live on two levels the public level which
is our doing.
Observable. Verifiable.
And the private stage.
The thinking states that are housing stage in
which we prepare for future roles.
We plan for the roles we want to play.
For the means whereby we have to organize in
order to.
Do what you want to do.
Now, it sounds a bit peculiar that this is
still thinking in the way,
making it just a part of role playing.
However, when you look a bit Deep into your
existence,
our existence, my existence.
You will realize that the pure biological
being.
The gratification of our instincts.
Our sex survival. Breathing plays only a
minor part in our preoccupation.
Especially in a country where we're so
spoiled,
like in the States where even we don't know
what it means to be hungry.
Where anyone who wants to have sex can have
sex plentiful.
Anyone who wants to breathe can breathe.
The air is tax free. Even the smog in Los
Angeles is free.
For the rest. We play games.
We play games to an extent openly into much
greater extent privately.
Do you think we mostly talk to somebody?
Sometimes we might communicate.
Most times we should. No time.
We hypnotize each other.
We hypnotize ourselves that we are right.
You play Madison Avenue to convince other
people or ourselves of our value.
And this takes up so much of our energy
again,
that sometimes, if you are unsure about the
role you're playing,
you wouldn't dare to say a word a sentence
without having it first.
Again and again until it fits the occasion.
Now, if you're not sure of the role you want
to play.
And you're called away from your pilot stage
to the public stage like every good actor,
you experience stage fright.
Stage fright is called anxiety.
Anxiety is nothing but stage fright.
Your excitement is only mounting.
You want to play a role.
But you don't quite dare.
So you go back to restrict your breathing.
But the heart pumps out more blood because
the higher metabolism has to be satisfied.
And then once you are on stage.
And play the role, the excitement flows into
your performance.
If not, your performance would be rigid.
It's very difficult for us to understand that
we are always playing.
So no wonder when we try to understand the
essence of a neurosis that on the first level
we find what I call the Sigmund Freud layer,
the role playing layer.
We Would behave as if.
We pretend to be better.
Tougher. More polite. And so then you really
feel.
And you see, when I spoke yesterday about
manipulation.
Whether the child has to play helpless.
Stupid. Polite. Flattering.
The child in doing so,
develops the habit of using this type of
manipulation and habit is nothing but a
performance of the same action that goes
easier and easier. It's a grooving of one's
activity that then becomes a habit,
(Transcribed by Sonix.ai - Remove this message by upgrading your Sonix account)
a character, a fixed role.